[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defus and
welcome to Hol talk the internet's laser
and holography talk show enjoyed in over
42 countries throughout the world and
now here's this week's
[Music]
show hello everyone this is Frank defus
and welcome to the 2004 opening show of
holot talk now going into its eighth
year of broadcasting on the internet my
special guest for this show is Graham
Saxby who will be joining us via
satellite connection from the holot talk
Studio to his home in England as you may
or may not already be aware Graham has
just recently release the Third Edition
of practical holography which many
people myself included consider the
authoritative working manual for all
things
holographic I was contacted by his
publisher several weeks ago asking if I
would review the book and decided to up
the ante by suggesting that we do a live
program with graham to broadcast an
association with the book's release the
book is already available in England and
amazon.com has February 2004 posted as
its release date here in the US for
those listeners who would like to order
a copy in the UK along with those
listeners in the US that would like to
pre-order a copy I've included links on
the the holot talk page to amazon.com in
both the US and
UK I'd like to welcome all of the holot
talk listeners who have tuned into the
program and look forward to Bringing
additional programming throughout the
upcoming year it's always a pleasure and
an honor to be your host and now without
further delay here's Graham
Saxby hello everyone this is Frankie
frus and I have Graham Saxby on the line
how are you today Graham oh I'm fine
thank you yeah hello Frank how are
things on the other side of the pond
well a bit dull today and not very warm
but uh it looks like being a reasonable
sort of winter I hope that's nice that's
nice we're getting ready to go into a
very cold period here where would be
down in single digits and below zero oh
yes within the next week so and and to
and the past few days we were out with
t-shirts on so it's a quite a difference
yes how are you overall well we we've
been without te shirts for some time now
but it hasn't been really cold we we get
a bit of frost but uh in this part of
the world it's generally fairly warm
because we're we're fairly near some big
cities yes yes well we have we have a
very good connection yes so we're
thankful for that and I I thought we
would start off the interview by uh
jumping right into a few questions that
I'm sure a lot of the listeners have out
there and that is when the first edition
of practical holography came out in
1988 um it was well received and almost
instantaneously went into what we would
say could be the Bible of practical
practice of holography with the new
edition what's new oh well
um with the first edition really I was
just sort of putting together everything
that I knew about holography at the time
and uh as time went on it became more
and more obvious that there were bits
missing and things had moved on a bit
and U I went into a second edition and
now of course things have moved on again
and the most important thing of course
being that um lasers have suddenly come
down in price we've got diode lasers
which are really very good and people
can now pretty well literally make
holograms on the kitchen table yeah so
of course that was the first thing that
had to be amended and I had to put in
that sort of thing and some of us in the
Royal photographic society's holography
group have been doing quite a lot of
work on doing little workshops showing
people how they can make Holograms with
very simple lasers the sort of thing you
can buy in souvenir shops yeah I
actually bought one in Greece for under
two pound sterling and you couldn't even
buy the batteries in this country for
that sort of money and and really we've
been able to get quite good Holograms
I've done a lot of work with with Jeff
BL is a bit of an expert in the
processing system and he's involved some
very good
processing and the other thing of course
is that I've had to bring some of the um
applied holography up to date yes and
I've been keeping up with that because
um I have a company that U supplies me
with AB racts and I've got abstracts of
every paper that's been written on
holography or even mentioning holography
for the last 25 years so it's fairly
easy to keep up with that but it it's
rather surprising going through the
previous Edition um how little has
really been done yes and as far as as
far as display holography is concerned
really I think we reached the peak
several years ago MH and not very much
more has happened people have just got
better at it yeah
but of course there have been big
advances in data processing and that
sort of thing and um particularly in
embossed holography and security and so
forth yes that's I had to completely
rewrite the chapter on security
holography I guess I guess the answer
with electronic holography and the
transmission of this information is
going to come through uh compression oh
yes yes very much so and there's there's
a lot of work really um to be done with
um well you can call it electr
holography or something of that sort but
really it's um
using
um using electronic Imaging to produce
the objects for the holography rather
than anything else the other thing is of
course that with electronic Imaging we
still haven't really got down to the
sort of resolution that you need to make
the traditional sort of holograms with
off axis beams yeah at the moment they
can still really only make satisfactory
Holograms either with on axis beams like
garbor Holograms or the slightly
off-axis ones that you have with foror
transform
holograms for transform Holograms are
the the main sort of thing in data
processing right I remember back in the
late '70s perhaps early 80s and I think
the company was named aerodine but they
had a holographic printer that would
write out a computer generated hologram
pixel by pixel and I believe it took
like 12 hours for a 1 cm square area to
be written yes it would um that was one
of the troubles that um Steve Benson's
team had when they were trying to
produce holographic video MH they they
found that it would take 25 minutes to
print out a single um
television um picture yeah and of course
that really that was um how Benson's
rainbow Holograms came about because he
was trying to reduce the amount of
information by cutting out the vertical
Parallax MH and he finished up with a
rainbow hologram rather I think to his
surprise than everybody else's yeah and
of course that was the start of the
whole business of commercial OST
Holograms yeah that's amazing story with
the uh development of the rainbow
hologram basically due to the fact that
uh they were trying to decrease the
amount of information it would have to
be transmitted and written that's right
yeah yeah so we were all devastated when
Steve died of course yes very very sad
indeed yeah one one of the great
pioneers and such a wonderful fellow too
and I was proud to call him a friend of
mine Yeah we actually have an interview
on The holot Talk archive page with
Steve so if any of the listeners who are
new to the show have not have an
opportunity to U hear Steve Benton
there's a there's a show on the page
there oh yeah as well and I want to
thank you very much for uh coming on the
show by the way and and also for having
the publisher send that copy of the book
and um as usual it's an excellent book
and uh so so you're saying basically uh
what you feel are the the largest areas
uh of of inclusion or or new areas of
inclusion in the book would be uh the uh
diode holography and also several new
formulas that you have in the book as
well oh yes very much so and I I have to
be very grateful to Jeff blly for that
as well because he spent a lot of time
not only working out how to make red
sensitive di chromate but um how to make
your own holographic Emulsion from
scratch yes he's working in Cambridge
University at the moment um not on
holography as such but um using
holographic emotions in diagnostic
things what what he did very roughly is
to make a trivial hologram that is a
just a hologram of a mirror and then he
um subjects it to various sorts of
things you know bacteria and so forth
and from the color changes it's possible
to diagnose what's going on MH so it's
quite an exciting thing but it's not
direct holography as such yeah on the
other hand he has to have reliable
emulsions and so he had to work out how
to make them himself mhm and that of
course is something that I've been able
to publish in this new edition well
that's wonderful that that's in the book
and it's out there now the other thing
about it of course is that I I have
Rewritten the format completely MH then
the old one it was a bit text bookish
and um I've really taken the leaf out of
the open University's book and what they
do because they distance learning thing
their textbooks have to be pretty close
to having a tutor breathing down your
neck MH and therefore they they're all
sort of first person and uh you know
this is what I'm telling you kind of
thing yes and U they to keep the
continuity all the anecdotes and various
little side bits are actually put in
margins and the smaller diagrams go into
margins as well and that gives a much
better continuity yes and I I tried this
in the first place in the last book
which I did which wasn't altogether
about holography it was called the
science of Imaging and uh that was it's
about photography and television and
video and holography and everything
else and it worked so well that I I
thought I'd like to try the same format
for practical holography when we came to
rewrite it yeah it appears it's been
through a number of different Publishers
it started off with Apprentice Hall M
and Apprentice Hall um of course like
all these other firms say tremendous lot
of selling out to different companies
goes on and they finished up with
Pearson Education who found they hadn't
really got room for a book of that type
on their books and by very good fortune
I got in with the Institute of physics
publishing and I was doing some
freelance editing for them and they
thought it would be a very good idea to
take this book under the their wing as
it were and they they really have been
absolutely first class they've been
tremendously
helpful it does seem to appear that it's
evolved into somewhat more of a uh
beside the table workbook where
everything is broken down into
step-by-step modules exactly yes yes
that was just what I wanted to do in the
first place see when when I was actually
working
and partly uh at the Royal College of
Art and partly at w Hampton University
and I had these students and of course I
had to teach them as it were breathing
down their shoulders and I thought the
best thing I could do was to put that
into words as best I could mhm because I
mean I was getting older and I was
already beyond my retiring age and
they'd stopped paying me a salary people
were sort of breathing down my neck and
saying you know we we need this place we
need more office space What are you
doing working in here you should have
been retired long ago I I think it
happens to a lot of people in academic
life do you of course as soon as they
got rid of me they turned the whole
place into offices and that was that I I
was very lucky to be able to pick up the
equipment around the back door for a
fairly small sum but I'm unfortunately I
wasn't able to build myself my own lab
which I would have liked to do so and I
I sold off the bits to various friends
of mine in the profession profession oh
you're you're going around you're going
around and lecturing now yes yes I'm not
an awful lot and I like to feel I have
been able to retire a bit and look after
the
garden I I still do writing and editing
of course how often do you make it to
the states do you come over um well I I
used to come over regularly to Tong
jong's symposia at Lake Forest M but I
haven't able to get hold of get over
recently really for family reasons MH so
uh I I just have to wish them
well I I'd like to get over to the
states again but I just haven't been
able to what what's the holography
community like in um England right now
um well the the uh autistic side is it's
a bit weak in numbers but it's pretty
strong in creativity we' still got
Margaret benan of course yes and just
received uh what is the award that she
received from the queen oh she got the
uh MBE that's it's s of a member of the
British
Empire it's rather out ofate sort of
name MH but it's um it's one of the
senior honors it's not quite as good as
a Knighthood
yeah so so she's not sir Margaret benan
no no no she's she's too not is below
that okay but um it's certainly the
really I think the first Royal
recognition of holography mhm although
she knows Prince Charles he actually
visited when she was working in
Australia wow and asked her about
holographic portraiture well in those
days there weren't any pulse lasers MH
so that wasn't possible but we still
live in hopes
mhm uh is the program at RAC still
intact no it is I I get emails all the
time asking me about um yes it would
have been lovely it really was good I
mean I had quite a hand in in starting
the thing up because Michael Langford
who was head of Photography at that time
another chap who very sadly died an
awful lot too early he um he and I put
the idea together and we designed the
rooms and Nick Phillips and organized
all the equipment and we put this thing
together and ALT together we um we Tau
about 30 35 students and they all became
professional biographers MH but the real
trouble was that the Royal College of
Art will only take graduates MH see they
only award master's degrees and doctor's
degrees and and they it was drying up
because all various universities were
gradually giving up um holographic Labs
yeah mine was the last in fact um
Liverpool poly Technic with um Rod
Murray was the next before last and when
Rod left that he actually took over the
RCA and um then eventually when mine
packed up there were no more
graduates and so there were no more
students yeah and that was that and once
again the administrators marched in and
said oh we need more office
base and in any case the equipment was
beginning to get a bit old and sort of
studentized those students that went on
to uh obtain their graduate degree at uh
Royal College of Art uh in holography um
are they finding
employment well most of them are still
working freelance a lot of them have got
sort of daytime jobs yes but there
there's still quite a few who are
exhibiting regularly
and um some of the others the original
technician Rob Munday has has got his
own um his own company down in Su and
they're doing very well making large
Holograms and doing Masters for
embossing and that sort of thing that's
probably similar to John Perry's company
here holographics North up in Burlington
Vermont would imagine yes very much like
that and a number of others have gone on
to work for various companies
and do their own thing in holography on
the side well you you started in
photography right I imagine were you um
doing Imaging for the Air Force or
something Royal Air Force yes that's
right um in just after the war I was
actually working um working in aircraft
industry on wind tunnels and I
absolutely hated the job and I wanted to
be a photographer I was already doing
quite a lot of freelance work and at
that time
we still had national service so when
you were 18 you you got called up that
is you you got drafted and you did two
years in the Army MH and I was working
in the air aircraft industry so I was
excused that but if I left the aircraft
industry of course I would immediately
be conscripted into the army and spend
two years washing out the trains or
whatever it is that National servicemen
do the only way I could get out of that
was to join the RAF as a foot
photographer and of course I when I did
that I got all all proper training all
the Technical Training and became well I
hope is quite a good technical
photographer was that aerial photography
um aerial photography comes into it a
lot yeah but I was lucky enough to get
quite a lot of jobs doing ground
photography okay where I did everything
I spent a lot of time doing public
relations in Germany and I met a lot of
uh very excit exting people I
photographed almost all the royal family
and the German people Conor had an our
own company and there was one occasion
when uh I had I photographed General
galland he was he was the Red Baron of
the second world war and he was
presented back with his Iron Cross by
the chap who had shot him down during
the Battle of Britain it was all very
exciting he was most delightful man and
had all sorts of exciting assignment and
also unfortunately had a few
post-mortems and and crashed aircraft
and things like that so you know you
just had everything yeah and but the
aerial reconnaissance photography of
course was the big thing in those days M
and now there isn't very much of it what
there is is mostly sort of lowlevel
stuff OB having a look inside Woods at
very low level the high level stuff is
all done by satellites yeah yeah
obviously your interest in this uh
gravitated more towards the
technical yes but I I did an immense
amount of piture and weddings and things
like that oh yeah so I mean my my
general interest is actually in in
Landscapes and
architecture I have huge file about
20,000 photographs looking at them now
that's stacked on the Shelf
about 3 m High 3 m wide and they're all
negatives and transparency yeah that
that seems to be the final frontier with
holography is just to be able to get
affordable emotions and that's where
Jeff's worth comes in yes that it is a
difficulty I mean it was an awful blow
when AGA packed up making their Emulsion
yeah I loved AGA plates in in a way of
course it was a good thing because the
ACT emotions weren't really very good
they're nice to work with they they they
were very
forgiving oh yes yes they had a
tremendous latitude I remember I was
trying to demonstrate the effects of
overexposure and
underexposure and I actually had to
underexpose by a factor of 10 before it
became visible yes and Overexposed by a
factor of nearly 50 yeah before you
could see any deterioration in the image
yeah it was it was real nice to keep
exposure time shorts because you could
always make it up in the development yes
yeah yes that that was another thing
that um Jeff and I evolved um Jeff got
the idea of using um a developer
containing pyro gallal pyro gallal is a
developer that was used and by the very
old photographers it was one of the
first developing agents still my
favorite pirate chome process yes well
that I we we sort of developed that
process and and and I got on to it
from process that we used to use in the
RAF and when people came back from
reconnaissance sorties with stuff that
have been grossly
underexposed and we used to use a
developer that contained paragallo and
metol M and this would give an increase
in exposure of anything up to three
stops yeah the quality was pretty awful
but at least you had an image mhm mhm
and and I I worked on this and
eventually came up with the formula
that's in my book with pyro and metol
and that gave tremendous contrast and it
held back some of the um some of the
noise that was typical of AGA MH um
because of the yellow stain that It
produced only trouble was it stained
everything else including your fingers
and clothes well you know photography uh
chemistry has a long history of uh
toxicity just across the board but we've
certainly come a long way away from the
days of U parabeno quinone the pbq and
the MCU chloride bleaches horrible stuff
yeah I I worked with both of those in
the early days yes so did I
yeah um the book is available now in the
UK I imagine someone can order that
right now yes yes it cost £55 Sterling
you can get it through Amazon of course
yes if anybody is really stuck then if
they get in touch with me I can sort
something out for them okay and and
amazon.com here in the US will actually
have it available I think they're going
to ship it in February 204 so they're
accepting pre-orders for the book now I
believe I believe so yes I haven't had a
look at their website
yeah5
us which just for the processing
formulas and the um emultion formulas
itself could pay for itself well it's
only the cost of a couple of large
plates isn't it yes oh my goodness I'll
tell you yeah yeah yes well in this
country as I said it's it's 55 Sterling
and so in in fact if you ordered it from
this country and had it shipped out by
um by uh surface it' probably be cheaper
than buying it in the
USA had you considered doing a
multimedia CD ROM at any point
no no to like be a supplement to the
book well um and I I sort of gave it
some thoughts and then thought no it's
um due to the production involved the
well no I'm I'm not really terribly well
up in in that particular bit of
technology in in fact I only bought a
computer when some of the stuff I was
writing the the Publishers demanded it
on on floppy discs yes and so I I had to
get a computer in order to produce it in
the format they wanted and I'm I've
being a sort of reluctant learner I I
work on what the services used to call a
need to know
basis soon as I need to know something I
I look it up and work out how to do it
do you get a chance to go out onto the
internet to uh see what's out there for
holography oh yes yeah there's a
wonderful Forum network 54 which um has
has cropped up which is a very active
community of uh holographs as well yes
yeah yes I've come across that
yeah and uh of course your interview
will be up and uh I'm going to head out
on the road after I finish this up and
uh I'll make sure that before I leave
today that the interview is up and that
the notice goes out to all of the holot
talk listeners and I hope you tune in to
listen to it as well well I certainly
shall yes is there anything probably
make me curl up just listening to it oh
no no no is is there anything that we
didn't cover that you'd like to say to
the listeners while we uh are on the
tail end of the interview here I can't
think of anything specific
and I appreciate all that you've done
for
holography oh well yes I I mean what I
the only thing that I really did do
apart from stealing everybody else's
ideas is to
um porography on as I said onto the
kitchenable table mhm you see there was
one particular aspect of holography that
always bothered me and that that was the
beam splitter and I felt the beam
splitter was a single object on the
table that made holography difficult and
made made bad Holograms because as soon
as you started turning one beam of light
one way and the other beam of light the
other way yeah you were turning them
through different bits of air yeah and
we certainly found that the the major
problem in big table holography was air
current yeah and defining big table by
the size would be well anything above 1
by two M yeah so you're talking about
your typical in US measurements your
typical 4x8 uh vibration T isolation
table that's right yes yes well the main
tables I used at wolver Hampton was um 1
and 1/2 by 2 and 1/2 M that's um about
uh 7 ft by 12 ft something like that and
uh that's a nice size yes yeah yes it
was lovely I I built a Gantry on top of
it and it made the whole thing very
rigid indeed is that the is that one of
the is that one of the pictures that's
in the book yes yeah okay yes that's
right yeah um the the main thing that
I've that I worked on um was what I I
had to co a name for it I called it a
bypass hologram and you didn't have to
have have a beam splitter at all because
you just used the two halves of a spread
beam and you reflected one um using a
mirror mhm into the other one so that um
you uh you actually had a mirror
alongside your object yes and the mirror
provided the reference beam and the
reflection for the object provided the
object beam you couldn't really get any
simpler than that and the two beams were
so close together that they were going
through very much the same a space yeah
I I believe there's an example of that
also at someone's website maybe I think
in Norway or something like that they're
using a technique very similar to that
very likely but it certainly worked it
it worked like a dream and I I never had
a bad hologram using that system I I
don't claim originality for the first
thought it was Hans bearen who thought
of it yeah um he had to make some
Holograms of things like Milling
machines on a factory floor mhm and so
he had to build a little dark room
around them and he used that method he
actually taped a mirror to the machine
itself yeah I know you Ed the term that
you you had stolen other people's ideas
but I don't I think that a better term
for that would be that you've just taken
other people's ideas and you've provided
the service of actually compiling those
ideas into one reference yeah well
that's a nice way of putting it yeah
that's that's essentially what it what
it is I mean we we both I was fortunate
enough to be able to discover um how to
make all the main types of holograms
using this same basic setup and that
really was quite exciting and I wrote a
paper for for Tong jong's Symposium
about it and it went down very well in
fact yeah and with the with the higher
defraction efficiencies of the newer
emulsions it's a wonderful thing too oh
yes it is yeah yes it really is well
Graham I want to thank you very much for
taking the time to uh come on the show
and uh speak about the book and I want
to remind the listeners one more time
that there there are links to both
amazon.com UK and amazon.com here in the
US where if you happen to be in England
listening to this you can order the book
and have it delivered now and the
release date in the United States is
February 2004 but you can pre-order that
book and have that shipped to you as
soon as it's available from Amazon
Graham thank you so much if you just
want to hold on the line for a second uh
I'll get